Guide to the Walt Whitman papers, 1841-1940, bulk 1841-1891 RL.01378
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1841-1891 and undated
  - Manuscript Prose, 1852-1891 and undated
    - Prefaces
      - "Struggling steadily to the front not only in the spirit of Opinion" (Volume 50)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink on two sheets of paper, about 8x5 inches, made up of various scraps pasted together; fifty-five lines, extensively revised. Bound in a royal octavo volume, cloth, orange morocco back. An early draft of the prefatory note to "Song of the Exposition," published in Two Rivulets. On the verso of the first sheet is part of a letter to Whitman, probably from John Burroughs [1874]; on the verso of the second appears a portion of a letter from Peter Doyle [1874], a five-line jotting by Whitman, and two more lines from the Burroughs letter.
    - Essays, Lectures, and Notes
      - "America needs her own poems, in her own body and spirit" (Volume 61)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one sheet of ruled paper, s .x. 6 inches. Recto: thirteen lines, revised. Verso: "[Th]ought never to be forgotten in lectures"; eleven lines, slightly revised. Bound in an octavo volume, boards. Both of these fragments express ideas embodied in the 1855 preface (Camden Edition, vi, 29; iii, 275-276).
      - "Canada lecture" (Volume 60)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on five sheets of paper, about 6x4 inches, one side only; forty-seven lines, revised. Bound in a duodecimo volume, cloth, green morocco back. Ideas for a lecture in Canada, 1880 (partly published in Diary in Canada, page 72).
      - "for Ottawa lecture" (Volume 57)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on three sheets of paper, two about 7x4 inches, one 3x5 inches, one side only; forty-two lines, revised. Bound in an octavo volume, boards. Notes on war, business, and the impressions gained by Whitman on his trip in Canada (Camden Edition, vi, 25-26).
      - "Founding a new American Religion (? No Religion)" (Volume 64)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil and ink on four pieces of paper, of various sizes and colors, one side only; about forty-five lines. Bound in a quarto volume, cloth, orange morocco back. Fragmentary notes on the subject of religion (Camden Edition, vi, 55, 139; iii, 280-281; vi, 149).
      - "It is no doubt impossible to say any thing not already said" (Volume 226)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink on sixteen pieces of paper, of various sizes, one side only; about 250 lines, revised in ink and pencil. Mounted in a folio volume, full green morocco, gilt tooled. A draft of a lecture on public education, intended for delivery in Washington, D.C., probably on the occasion of the dedication of a new school building in 1872. With a two-page letter, signed, from T. A. Walker, Acting Super intendent, Census Office, to Walt Whitman, 1871. Laid in: an issue of "Week-End," Sunday supplement to the Brooklyn Daily Eagle, July 12, 1936, containing a printed version of the manuscript, entitled "Education in Our Schools," edited by Anna Traubel.
      - "It is said, perhaps rather quizzically by one of my friends" (Volume 65)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one sheet of light brown paper, about 8x7 inches. Recto: sixteen lines. Verso: "my journey in Canada is blue line below"; a map of a portion of Canada. Bound in a small quarto volume, cloth. Notes for a lecture or essay expressing views on the supreme position of men and women (Diary in Canada, page 71), with a map drawn by Whitman to show the course of his journey in 1880.
      - "Italian singers in America" (Volume 66)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink on three sheets of paper, about 7x7 inches, one side only; forty-two lines. Bound in a small quarto volume, half brown morocco. A paragraph on the contralto Alboni, perhaps intended for newspaper publication. With a clipping headed "Whitman and Alboni," from the Poughkeepsie Daily News.
      - "Materialism" (Volume 44)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on the back of a piece of flowered wall-paper, about 8x8 inches; eighteen lines, revised. Bound in a quarto volume, boards. Notes for a lecture or essay dealing with evolution (Camden Edition, vi, 150-151).
      - "the mob, the trial of Warren Hastings, the death-bed of Robert Burns" (Volume 36)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one side of a sheet of paper, about 9x8 inches; about twenty-five lines. A rough draft of a portion of Whitman's essay on Elias Hicks.
      - The Old World (Europe and Asia) is the region of the poetry of the past (Volume 37)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, signed, written on one sheet of paper, about 9x8 inches. Recto: sixteen lines, written in blue pencil and revised in ink. Verso: a letter, dated February 9, 1890, from John W. Cook of Normal, Illinois, to Walt Whitman. Tipped in a small folio volume, marbled covers, half black morocco. A portion of the last paragraph of "Shakspere for America" (Camden Edition, iv, 22-23); in the letter on verso, Cook acknowledges receipt of a copy of Complete Poems and Prose, and asks Whitman to send him a bill for the book. Bookplate: A. Edward Newton. With an inscription by Newton.
      - "Our own account of this poem, 'the German Iliad' " (Volume 231)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink on one side only of four sheets of paper, about 12 x 7 inches; twenty-eight lines and thirty-eight verses. Bound in a folio volume, full blue morocco, gilt tooled, with white moire doublures. A prose account of the Nibelungenlied, followed by a translation of a part of the poem.
      - "? outset of lecture" (Volume 45)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one sheet of yellow paper, 10 x 8 inches, one side only; twenty-five lines. Bound in a quarto volume, half blue morocco. Ideas on the proper preparation for study—"self-teaching exercises" (Camden Edition, vi, 55-56).
      - "Rel." (Volume 229)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink on four sheets of paper, about 12x7 inches, one side only; about 105 lines. Mounted in a folio volume, cloth, orange morocco back. Notes intended to serve as a guide for the preparation of a lecture on religion (Camden Edition, vi, 192-195).
      - "Sculpture" (Volume 48)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written and revised in pencil on one sheet of paper, about 9x5 inches; eighteen lines. In a board folder. A portion of an essay or lecture presumably on the Greeks (Camden Edition, vi, 157).
      - "Slavery —the Slaveholders —The Constitution—the true America and Americans, the laboring persons" (Volume 228)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on twenty sheets of ruled paper, of various sizes, one side only; about 450 lines, revised in pencil and ink. Bound in a folio volume, full blue morocco, gilt tooled. Portions of several political speeches, combined perhaps to form a new one; one portion was apparently written in 1846, another deals with the Fugitive Slave Act.
      - "Spring of '59—read Dante's 'Inferno' " (Volume 54)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on four sheets of paper, about 8x6 inches, one side only; about eighty-two lines, revised in ink. Bound in an octavo volume, full undyed pigskin, gilt tooled. A short essay on Dante (Camden Edition, vi, 91-93).
      - "Wants" (Volume 43)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in blue and black inks on seven sheets of paper, about 12 x 8 inches, one side only; about 230 lines, revised in pencil and black ink. Bound in a small folio volume, half green morocco. An incomplete essay on labor advertisements and on the scenes in and around employment bureaus.
      - "A Word about Tennyson" (Volume 49)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, signed, written in ink on seven sheets of paper, about 11x6 inches, one side only; 189 lines, slightly revised, with instructions to the printer inserted in red ink. Bound in a small narrow folio volume, full red morocco. The copy from which the essay was printed in the Critic of January 1, 1887. Bookplate: A. Edward Newton.
    - Notes on Literature
      Listed alphabetically by headings or first lines.
      - Miscellaneous Notes, Chiefly Literary (Volume 225)
        Description from Frey: Ten autograph manuscripts, written in pencil and ink on ten pieces of paper, of various sizes; about 170 lines in all. Mounted in a small folio volume, half orange morocco. Headings: "The florid rich, first ? phases of poetry, as in the Oriental poems" (Camden Edition, vi, 96); "Europe" (vi, 218); "Milton —1608 —1674"; "The Teutonic includes the Scandinavian" (vi, 210); "(passing through the town of Borgo in old Finland, Russia,)" (vi, 95-96); "Specimen Days" (Diary in Canada, page 64); "—the story of Dante's 'Journey through Hell' " (Camden Edition, vii, 11); "Mithras, the grand deity of ancient Persians, supposed to be the sun" (vii, 22); " 'law' 'lex' 'lux' light? Alcoran signifies law" (vi, 214); "Of the Democratic Party 58—'59—60." On verso of "Europe": "Two Samples of Voltaires writings" (Camden Edition, vi, 218); notes on Voltaire. On verso of "Milton —1608 —1674": "Burns, born 1757 died 1796—aged 39" (vii, 8). Miscellaneous jottings on poetry and on the geography and population of Europe, a list of synonyms for the word "poet," geographical and ethnological definitions, observations on Finland copied from the New York Tribune for October, 1855, notes on events in 1854 and 1855 intended as a reminder for Specimen Days, names of Italian poets, scraps on Mithras and various religions of the Orient, a vitriolic remark on the planks of the Democratic platform, 1858-1860, and notes on literary men.
      - Notes on Literature (Volume 232)
        Description from Frey: Thirteen autograph manuscripts, written in ink and pencil on sixteen pieces of paper, of various sizes; about 200 lines in all. Mounted in a quarto volume, full red morocco, gilt tooled, moire doublures; in a red cloth slipcase, morocco tipped. Headings: "The celebrated old German poem we are going to make a running sketch of" (Camden Edition, vi, 187); "Read'g Shakespeare" (vi, 189); "Richard Burbage, principal owner in theatre, & principal actor" (vi, 189); "good statement" (vi, 197); "The relation between the mass of employ'd persons on one side" (vi, 188-189); "America has been called proud and arrogant" (vi, 197); "The idea (illustrated by Kant) that it isn't those who travel the most" (vi, 188); "A poem theme Be happy" (vi, 202); "With all Macpherson's restorations or someth'g worse there is a certain race" (vi, 187-188); "Books, as now produced, have reached their twentieth remove from verities" (vi, 198); "In the pleantiful [sic] feast of romance presented to us" (vi, 198); "fervor out of which wayward forms arose. —Complaint?" (vi, 186); "those stages, Egyptian, Hindu, Hebraic, Greek, Christian" (vi, 186). Verso of "America has been called proud and arrogant": a fragment on the graceful school in American and English literature. Miscellaneous notes: on the Nibelungenlied, Shakespeare, Burbage, the importation of forms and laws from Europe, the labor problem, the backwardness of America in literature, travel, a theme for a poem, Ossian, the shortcomings of "literary literature," and the great soul of man as exhibited in the past stages of human accomplishment.
      - "1855 —I have looked over Gerald Massey's Poems. London" (Volume 73)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one sheet of paper, about 9x5 inches, one side only; twelve lines, slightly revised in ink. In a board folder. Notes on the poetry of Gerald Massey (Camden Edition, vi, 157).
      - "? But Though so loving, so singing, so dwelling on the past" (Volume 99)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink and pencil on one sheet of ruled paper, about 4x6 inches, one side only; eleven lines. Fragmentary remarks on a poet, probably Tennyson.
      - "Diderot (Dennis Diderot)" (Volume 92)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one piece of ruled paper, about 5x4 inches; nineteen lines. On the verso Whitman has written in ink his name and the address "Closson Avenue near Myrtle Av Brooklyn." In a board folder. A brief outline of the career of Diderot (Camden Edition, vi, 226).
      - "Dr. Priestly (or Priestley)" (Volume 74)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one sheet of pink paper, about 10 x 6 inches, one side only; twenty-eight lines. Bound in an octavo volume, half orange morocco. Notes on Priestley, based on a conversation with a Unitarian preacher, "March 1 '57" (Camden Edition, vi, 129).
      - "Dryden 1631 to 1701" (Volume 72)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one sheet of pink paper, about 10 x 6 inches, one side only; eight lines. Bound in a royal octavo volume, half orange morocco. A brief impression of Dryden (Camden Edition, vi, 127-128). Attached to the bottom of the sheet are four clippings, consisting of brief sketches of Jeremy Taylor, Smollett, Pascal, and Franklin, from Half-Hours with the Best Authors, compiled by Charles Knight, New York, 1849 (1, 90, 324, 350-351,391).
      - "Edmund Spenser" (Volume 91)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink on three sheets of ruled paper, about 8x4 inches, one side only; eighty-eight lines. Bound in a duodecimo volume, full undyed morocco, gilt and blind tooled. An outline of the career of Spenser (Camden Edition, vi, 77-79).
      - " 'Even now Jasmund, the people's poet, prefers to sing in Provencal' " (Volume 86)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil and ink on both sides of two sheets of pink paper, about 10 x 6 inches; eighty-one lines. Bound in an octavo volume, half orange morocco. Miscellaneous notes on Jacques Jasmin (Camden Edition, vi, 93), Pythagoras (vi, 94), Ossian (vi, 94), Greek literature and history (vii, 9; vi, 98-99), Zoroaster (vi, 99), and other subjects, including a remark on Leaves of Grass, dated September, 1856 (vi, 43). A clipping on Jasmin, the Provencal poet, is pasted on the first page, with a note by Whitman, "early in '57." On the second page is mounted a clipping from Ossian, "Sect. CCLXXIV.—The Sun."
      - "Frances Wright" (Volume 76)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one sheet of pink paper, about 10 x 6 inches, one side only; twenty-six lines. Bound in an octavo volume, half green morocco. Notes on the life of Fanny Wright, derived from a "talk with Mrs. Rose Feb. 9th, '57" (Camden Edition, vi, 129-130).
      - "Frederick Schlegel 1772-1829" (Volume 93)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink on one sheet of blue paper, about 9x6 inches, one side only; thirty lines. Bound in an octavo volume, half green morocco. Notes on the life and philosophy of Schlegel (Camden Edition, vi, 120-121).
      - "Goethe —from about 1750 to 1832" (Volume 80)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on two sheets of yellow paper, about 10 x 5 inches, one side only; forty-five lines. Bound in a royal octavo volume, full orange morocco, gilt and blind tooled. Notes on Goethe (Camden Edition, vi, 113-114). Pasted on the verso of the first page is a clipping, "The True Character of Goethe."
      - "Goethe's Complete works, last complete edition of his own revision" (Volume 81)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on both sides of two sheets of pink paper, about 10 x 6 inches; 120 lines, revised in ink. Bound in a royal octavo volume, full brown morocco, gilt and blind tooled. Notes on, and impressions of, Goethe (Camden Edition, vi, 110-113). The manuscript includes the following dates: "January 1856," "Feb. 18 '56," "Feb. 22."
      - "He is a precursor, in some sort of great differences" (Volume 85)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one sheet of yellow paper, about 8x5 inches, one side only; twenty-three lines. Bound in an octavo volume, half black morocco. Notes on Swedenborg (Camden Edition, vi, 79-80). With a lengthy clipping on Swedenborg, headed "The New Jerusalem," annotated by Whitman.
      - "His earliest printed plays 1597 Romeo Juliet" (Volume 90)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink on eight sheets of paper, about 8x5 inches; about 225 lines, revised in pencil. The sheets are blank on verso, except for the sixth, on the back of which are pasted two clippings on Shakespeare, and the seventh, on the verso of which Whitman wrote thirty lines in pencil. Bound in an octavo volume, full black morocco, gilt tooled. Notes on the life and work of Shakespeare; the passage in pencil consists of notes from an article on the Shakespeare-Bacon controversy, "Illustrated London News Oct. 25, 1856" (Camden Edition, vi, 71-77). With Whitman's essay, "A Thought on Shakspeare," clipped from the Critic, August 14, 1886.
      - "The Iliad The Bible (? The Eschylean tragedies) " (Volume 94)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink on two sheets of blue paper, about 5x5 and 8x5 inches, one side only; thirty-nine lines, revised. Bound in an octavo volume, cloth, blue morocco back. Ideas on the Iliad and the Bible, especially the latter (Camden Edition, vi, 100).
      - "J. J. Rousseau" (Volume 79)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil and ink on both sides of two sheets of paper, about 8x4 and 3x5 inches; fifty-eight lines. Bound in an octavo volume, half orange morocco. An outline of a biographical sketch of Rousseau (Camden Edition, vi, 80-81).
      - "(Jean Paul) Friedrich Richter" (Volume 82)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on two sheets of pink paper, about 10x6 inches, one side only; fifty-nine lines. Bound in a royal octavo volume, cloth, green morocco back. Notes on the life of Richter with impressions of his style and a final observation on Carlyle as a transmitter of German transcendentalism and sentimentalism (Camden Edition, vi, 121-123).
      - "Lafontaine, born about 1621 lived 73 years— (1694)" (Volume 78)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one sheet of paper, about 9x5 inches, one side only; ten lines. In a board folder. Notes on the career of La Fontaine (Camden Edition, vi, 109). A clipping on the Comte de Buff on, from Half-Hours with the Best Authors (1,155) is mounted on the sheet.
      - "Louis 14th born 1638—died 1715 Corneille" (Volume 77)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one sheet of pink paper, about 10 x 6 inches, one side only; nineteen lines. In a board folder. Notes on French drama of the age of Louis XIV, on Rachel, the actress, and on Alfieri (Camden Edition, vi, 82).
      - "Memory —Nothing makes this faculty so good, as the employment of it.—Locke" (Volume 84)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink and pencil on one sheet of pink paper, about 10 x 6 inches, one side only; thirty-eight lines. Bound in an octavo volume, half black morocco. Notes on the life of Plutarch, preceded by a quotation from Locke and an observation on the great poet as making his own laws (Camden Edition, vi, 67, 126-127).
      - "The Nibelungen"
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on a scrap of paper, about 3x5 inches, one side only; four lines. Mounted inside the front cover of Voices from the Press, New York, 1850. A fragmentary note on the Nibelungenlied. See: http://search.library.duke.edu/search?id=DUKE002204119
      - "Oliver Goldsmith" (Volume 89)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on two sheets of ruled paper, about 6x4 inches, one side only; thirty-five lines. Bound in a 16mo volume, cloth, green morocco back. An outline of a biographical sketch of Goldsmith (Camden Edition, vi, 118- 119).
      - "*Shakspeare and Walter Scott are indeed limners and recorders" (Volume 117)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one sheet of blue paper, about 8x4 inches, one side only; eighteen lines, revised in pencil and ink. Bound in an octavo volume, half blue morocco. A declaration of his purpose to be a master, like Shakespeare and Scott, but a master of emotion, freedom, personality, and democracy (Camden Edition, vi, 84).
      - "Schiller—born 1759—died 1806" (Volume 83)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one sheet of yellow paper, about 10 x 6 inches; twenty-two lines. Bound in an octavo volume, half green morocco. Notes on various German poets (Camden Edition, vi, 114; vii, 12). On the verso are pasted two clippings, the first describing Goethe as a youth, the second as an old man; with an annotation by Whitman.
      - "Shelley, born 1792—died 1822 Keats died 1821" (Volume 75)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on a piece of paper, about 5x4 inches, evidently a portion of a proof sheet of a grammar; twenty-one lines. In a board folder. Notes on Shelley (Camden Edition, vi, 84). With: three pages of an article on the "Characteristics of Shelley" {American Whig Review, v (May, 1847), 533-536); two clippings, one on the misfortunes, the other on the vanity, of literary men; a copy of Shelley's "To a Skylark" clipped from Half-Hours with the Best Authors (1, 411-414). Whitman has annotated these items.
      - "The Social Contract, Or, Principles of Right" (Volume 100)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in ink on eleven sheets of ruled paper, about 10 x 8 inches, one side only; about 310 lines. Bound in a quarto volume, full green morocco, gilt tooled. A fair copy of extracts from a translation of Rousseau, with a few observations by Whitman, marked "original."
      - "The Song of Hiawatha by H. W. Longfellow" (Volume 71)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on one sheet of paper, about 9x5 inches, one side only; seven lines, revised. In a board folder. A brief jotting on Whitman's reaction to Hiawatha (Camden Edition, vi, 156-157).
      - "Torquato Tasso" (Volume 95)
        Description from Frey: Autograph manuscript, written in pencil on four sheets of ruled blue paper, about 7x4 inches, one side only; about 120 lines. Bound in a duodecimo volume, half brown morocco. An outline of a biographical sketch of Tasso (Camden Edition, vi, 163-166).
      - List of Whitman's favorite authors (Volume 223)
        Holograph manuscript containing a list of his favorite authors, with a note on that list, along with 25 annotated magazine exerpts and clippings. Bound in royal half-blue polished morocco binding.
    - Autobiographical Manuscripts
      - "24 Feb. 1891 In Notes if convenient" (Volume 132)
        Description from Frey: 5x8 inches; ten lines, revised. Verso: an autograph letter, signed, from Mrs. J. S. Harris to Whitman, February 22, 1891, Cumberland Centre, Maine. A paragraph on his health and publishing activities, in tended for publication in a newspaper or magazine. The letter is a request for the poet's autograph.
      - "(Elan E. Kelsey) Feb. 24— 1865 Eugene Kelsey" (Volume 130)